<!-- ------------------------------------------------------------------- -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!--  intro.xml           IdRel documentation             Chris Wensley  -->
<!--                                                    & Anne Heyworth  -->
<!--  version 2.31, 01/06/2015                                           -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!-- ------------------------------------------------------------------- -->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<Chapter Label="intro">
<Heading>Introduction</Heading>

This manual describes the &idrel; package for &GAP; 4.7 
for computing the identities among relators of a group presentation 
using rewriting, logged rewriting, monoid polynomials, module polynomials 
and <M>Y</M>-sequences.
<P/>
The theoretical background for these computations is contained in 
Brown and Huebschumann <Cite Key="BrHu" />, 
Brown and Razak Salleh <Cite Key="BrSa" /> and is surveyed in 
the first author's thesis <Cite Key="anne-thesis" />.
<P/>
&idrel; is primarily designed for the computation of a minimal set 
of generators for the module of identities among relators. 
It also contains functions which compute logged rewrite systems 
for group presentations (and complete them where possible); 
functions for operations involving elements of monoid rings; 
and functions for operations with elements of right modules over 
monoid rings.
The <M>Y</M>-sequences are used as a <E>rewriting</E> way of representing 
elements of a free crossed module 
(products of conjugates of group relators and inverse relators).
The package is written entirely in &GAP;4, and requires no compilation.
<P/>
The package is loaded into &GAP; with the <C>LoadPackage</C> command, 
and on-line help is available in the usual way.
<Example>
<![CDATA[
gap> LoadPackage( "idrel" ); 
gap> ?idrel
]]>
</Example>

A pdf version of the &idrel; manual is available 
in the <F>doc</F> directory of the home directory of &idrel;.

The information parameter <C>InfoIdRel</C> has default value <C>0</C>.
When raised to a higher value, additional information is printed out.

&idrel; was originally developed in 1999 using &GAP;3, 
partially supported by a University of Wales Research Assistantship 
for the first author, Anne Heyworth.
<P/>
If you use &idrel; to solve a problem then please send a short email to 
the second author, to whom bug reports, suggestions and other comments 
should also be sent. 
You may reference the package by mentioning <Cite Key="HeWe1" />
and <Cite Key="anne-thesis" />.
<P/>
The current version is &VERSION; of &LONGRELEASEDATE;. 
</Chapter>
