
<Chapter Label="ch:intro"><Heading>Introduction and Overview</Heading>

<Section Label="sec:intro"><Heading>Introduction</Heading>

The motivation of the package <Package>Browse</Package> was to provide 
better functionality for displaying two-dimensional arrays of data (e.g.,
character tables): moving through the data without loosing row and
column labels, searching for text, displaying extra information, hiding
information, allowing interactive user input, ...
<P/>
We wanted to achieve this by using the capabilities of the terminal
emulations in which &GAP; is running, and not by some external graphical 
user interface. For this we have chosen to use the widely available 
<C>C</C>-library <C>ncurses</C>, see <Cite Key="NCursesWeb"/>.

It contains functions to find out terminal capabilities,
to change properties of terminals, to place text, to handle several windows
with overlapping, ...  To use these functions the terminal is switched
to a <Emph>visual mode</Emph> <Index>visual mode</Index>
so that the display of the non-visual 
mode of your terminal in which &GAP; is running is not clobbered.
<P/>
<Package>Browse</Package> has now three levels of functionality:
<List >
<Mark>A low level interface to <C>ncurses</C></Mark>
<Item>
  This may be interesting for all kinds of applications which want
  to display text with some markup including
  <Index>colors as text attributes</Index>colors,
  maybe in several windows, 
  using the available capabilities of a terminal.
</Item>
<Mark>A medium level interface to a generic function <Ref
Func="NCurses.BrowseGeneric"/></Mark>
<Item>
  This is for displaying two-dimensional arrays of data, handles
  labels for rows and columns, searching, sorting, binding keys to
  actions, ...
  If you want to implement such applications for further kinds of data,
  first look at the examples
  in Section <Ref Func="BrowseData.IsBrowseTable" Style="Number"/>,
  then check what can be copied from the examples
  in Chapter <Ref Chap="ch:appl"/>,
  and consult the descriptions
  in Chapters <Ref Chap="chap:browse-user"/>
  and <Ref Chap="chap:browse-prg"/>.
</Item>
<Mark>Applications of these interfaces</Mark>
<Item>
  We provide some applications of the <C>ncurses</C> interface and
  of the generic <Ref Func="NCurses.BrowseGeneric"/> function. These may be
  interesting for end users, and also as examples for programmers of
  further applications. This includes (of course) a method for
  browsing through character tables, functions for browsing through data
  collections, several games,<Index>game</Index>
  and an interface for demos.
</Item>
</List>

Users interested only in these applications should perhaps just try
<C>NCurses.Demo()</C>.

</Section>

<Section Label="sec:overview"><Heading>Overview</Heading>

<Subsection Label="ssec:ov_ncurses">
<Heading>The <C>ncurses</C> interface</Heading>

Chapter <Ref Chap="ch:curses"/> describes &GAP;'s interface to the
<C>ncurses</C> <C>C</C>-library. The imported <C>C</C>-functions are shortly
explained, but for further details we refer to the documentation of that
library. There are also a few utility functions on &GAP; level, such as
<Ref Func="NCurses.SetTerm"/>, which simplify the use of the library.
<P/>
The concept of an <Emph>attribute line</Emph><Index>attribute line</Index>,
see <Ref
Func="NCurses.IsAttributeLine"/>, helps to deal with text with markup
for its display in a terminal window.
<P/>
This chapter is for users who want to write their own applications of
<C>ncurses</C>.
</Subsection>

<Subsection Label="ssec:ov_ncappl"><Heading>Applications of 
<C>ncurses</C></Heading>
In Chapter <Ref Chap="ch:util"/> we describe some interactive applications 
of the  <C>ncurses</C> interface. For example, there is <Ref
Func="NCurses.Select"/> for asking a user to choose one or several of a
given list of items. There is also a demo function <Ref
Func="NCurses.Demo"/> which we use to
demonstrate features of the <Package>Browse</Package> package, but it
may be interesting for other kinds of demos as well. 
</Subsection>

<Subsection Label="ssec:ov_genbrowse">
<Heading>The interface to browse two-dimensional arrays</Heading>
Chapters <Ref Chap="chap:browse-user"/> and <Ref
Chap="chap:browse-prg"/> describe the interface to a
generic function <Ref Func="NCurses.BrowseGeneric"/> which can be used for an
interactive display of two-dimensional arrays of data. The first of
these covers the basic functionality which may be sufficient for many
applications and the second gives more technical details. With
interactive display we mean that it is not only possible to scroll
through the data, but one can search for strings, sort by rows or columns,
select entries, bind arbitrary actions to keys and mouse events,
ask for help, and more.
</Subsection>

<Subsection Label="ssec:ov_browseappl">
<Heading>Applications of the generic function
<C>NCurses.BrowseGeneric</C></Heading>
In Chapter <Ref Chap="ch:appl"/> we describe several applications which
are using the generic <Ref Func="NCurses.BrowseGeneric"/> interface
introduced before.
They are provided as prototype applications and so we include some
implementation remarks in their documentation. 
<P/>
Users who just want to use these applications hopefully do not need to 
read this <Package>Browse</Package> manual, all applications are coming
with built-in help windows.
<P/>
There are different kinds of applications. 
First, there are  methods for browsing through character tables and tables
of marks (our original motivation for this package). Then there are
applications for browsing through data collections, e.g., the data
available through the <Package>AtlasRep</Package> package, the &GAP;
bibliography or the sections of the &GAP; manuals. Finally, there are
several games like Sam Loyd's fifteen puzzle (generalized), peg solitaire,
and Sudoku (including functions to create new puzzles and to solve
puzzles).
</Subsection>
</Section>


<Section Label="sec:pkg_userprefs">
<Heading>User preferences provided by the &Browse; package</Heading>

<Subsection Label="subsec:EnableMouseEvents">
<Heading>The user preference <C>EnableMouseEvents</C></Heading>

This user preference defines whether mouse events are enabled by default
in visual mode (value <K>true</K>) or not
(value <K>false</K>, this is the default).
During the &GAP; session, the value can be changed using
<Ref Func="NCurses.UseMouse"/>.
Inside browse applications based on <Ref Func="NCurses.BrowseGeneric"/>
or <Ref Func="NCurses.Select"/>,
the value can be toggled usually by hitting the <B>M</B> key.

</Subsection>

<Subsection Label="subsec:SelectHelpMatches">
<Heading>The user preference <C>SelectHelpMatches</C></Heading>

In the case that the &GAP; help system finds multiple matches,
<K>true</K> (the default) means that the user can choose one entry
from a list that is shown via <Ref Func="NCurses.Select"/>,
and <K>false</K> means that the matches are just shown in a pager.

</Subsection>

<Subsection Label="subsec:SelectPackageName">
<Heading>The user preference <C>SelectPackageName</C></Heading>

In the case that <Ref Func="LoadPackage" BookName="ref"/> is called
with a prefix of some package names,
<K>true</K> (the default) means that the user can choose one matching entry,
and <K>false</K> means that the matches are just printed.

</Subsection>

</Section>

</Chapter>

